There are sutas where wanderers of other
sects also teach the five hindrances.
But when asked about the difference
between their teaching and the Buddha's
teaching, the Buddha replies that if
those wanderers of other sects were
asked if there is a way of exposition by
which the five hindrances become 10,
then they would not know how to answer
and become more confused.
>> The Buddha then goes on to teach how the
five hindrances become 10. Mhm.
>> And he says whatever sensual desire
there is for the internal is a hindrance
and whatever sensual desire there is for
the external is also a hindrance.
>> Mhm.
>> Same for ill will. Can we discuss what
is meant by internal and external here?
>> Mhm. So
So
I think the most practical basically way
to um for somebody to to wrap their head
around it
would be
um external
is uh regarding the sense objects
but that also means
your thoughts concerned about sense
objects.
would be external
and then internal
again practically speaking say you could
discern the internal
you can't just turn your senses or your
attention towards it because that's not
it never appears as an object of your
senses I mean you know you could say
well internally it's the sense basis and
so on but it's like what is sense basis
practically speaking
How do you how do you look for them when
you can't see them directly? Your eye
cannot see uh itself. It can only see
the sights. And if for whatever reason
your eye sees the organ of itself in the
mirror, it sees the sight of it. Does
not see itself seeing it. So the only
way to discern the internal is that kind
of um as you often say um indirect way
through that like a peripheral
recognition or like even like like
self-awareness like awareness of
yourself in a situation
that's already a form of experiencing
the internal counterpart.
So instead of you just being absorbed
with the senses, you see yourself or
discern yourself being absorbed with the
sense objects. Sorry, not senses. So you
being instead of being absorbed with the
sense objects, you see yourself being
absorbed with the sense objects.
That second experience is like revealing
the internal counterpart. So then you
could have well and sensuality obviously
permeates both. You know, sensuality is
manifested through through chasing the
sense objects, but uh fundamentally
both perspectives
that can be simultaneously present. Your
your kind of um focus on a sense object,
but then recognizing yourself being
absorbed with a sense object. Both of
those perspectives can be concurrent and
they are concurrent. It's just that you
don't necessarily discern them both. Um
but they're both within the domain of
centrality. So they would be both affected with ill
So they would be both affected with ill
will or with a possibility of ill will.
So then it's not enough to just say no
to sense objects for example that you
are essentially sort of craving for but
you need to sufficiently also see
yourself in the situation of craving for
sense objects and then lose overcome the
passion towards that situation of the
reflexive kind
and that's what the Buddha was
describing the sutas like yeah you can
be physically you need to be physically
withdrawn from the uh sensuality
but if your mind is also not dried up
from it you're not overcoming it
and that's that's what means drying up
your mind so like you can as I said say
you see something pleasant
something desirable and desire is
present if you just obviously act out of it and
if you just obviously act out of it and
pursue it there is no
there is no concurrent recognition of
that other internal perspective. There
is just continuation of the loss of
perspective and going down the rabbit
hole until kind of it runs out. Options
disappear, evaporate and then you might
kind of wake up afterwards. You scratch
your itch so hard and then it stops
itching and then it's like, "Oh, where
am I? What happened?" type of thing. You
kind of come out of a that haze of being
kind of um pulled further into
centrality because you gave in. So if
you're not say automatically doing that
but are still staying on the level of
okay this is the beautiful site that is
trying to pressure me. I'll say no to
it. I'll say no to it. I'll say no to
it. Or let me think something else. Let
me look at something else. Let me let me
look at the ugly to remove it. Let me
look this. Let me do that. Either way,
you're still not self-aware
of the experience as a whole. So the
internal dimension is still not
revealed. It's still not discerned. And
that's why I keep saying to people the
practice of assuba that the sutras
describe or practice of meta applies to
somebody basically who already sees the internal
basically who already sees the internal
sufficiently to the point he has
discerned chitta
because chitta can only be discerned
further internally so to speak.
Otherwise if you just think when you see beautiful
if you just think when you see beautiful
look at the ugly when you think bad
think positive. You see either way you
remain engaged with the sense objects
and its oppositions but you don't see
yourself being engaged with the sense
objects that is not permitted to arise
because obviously your view is still
locked onto sense object as the problem
but that's not where the sensuality
comes from.
So you could be countering sense objects
with your ugly sense objects but even
that's not the actual practice of
auba is when the there is a sense
objects that has that pressuring the
mind with the desire you recognize the
experience as a whole ah there is he as
the satipana he knows the mind of lust
as mind of lust so he knows there is a
mind infected with lust towards this and
that's what I see the whole thing and
now while the whole thing is there I can
also provide the mind on the basis of
the whole thing I can provide it with
the well that very thing that you are
infatuated with
body or or other tastes or or sounds and
so on is dangerous
carries disgust in and of itself. So now
you are rewriting the context of the the
involvement of desire. You're not just
trying to deny it and replace it. And
that can only be done that rewriting can
only be done internally on the basis of
internal. So if you are just dealing
with the external stuff, you're not
overcoming a hindrance.
But if through obvious necessary
restraint towards the external, you do
not just blindly try to deny when the
mind is affected with lust or ill will
or or or doubt, but you recognize
instead of that you recognize the
experience as a whole of mind infected
towards this mind affected towards that
and you cultivate that recognition
instead of just giving in either through
just acting out or trying to deny it.
And that's how you developed internal
sense basis sufficiently enough. So when
then both are included.
So when basically when all you can see
is your mind having a desire towards
this site or that sound or any object
where that's your starting point means
you would have overcome the view of
sensuality the assumption of sensuality.
Now you just see the mind wanting or not
wanting but you're completely disowning
the whole thing because it has been
discerned as oh I'm not doing this. I
were never doing this. Even these
desires that I thought were mine were
never mine. I just did not see the
internal framework
because I've been preoccupied of just
acting towards sense objects out of the
immediate pressure either through
affirming it or denying it. Either way I
was not looking internally. So that's
why the the beginning of that internal
recognition is self-awareness
like in any situation
in any experience pleasant, unpleasant
or neutral.
And that's why I always say like in the
beginning you have to endure things
rightly to get to see that hold on it's not
to get to see that hold on it's not
about getting rid of stuff in the way I
thought it was. Just counter it. just do
the opposite because you're still doing
that equally lacking awareness of that
internal counterpart. No, it's about
including everything. So first if you
habitually stop giving up giving giving
towards it like immediately jumping at
the what things whatever you're
pressured towards if you just
immediately go for it well that's a
problem. Whatever you're pressured
towards you don't immediately go for it
but you try to now get rid of that
experience as a whole. Again, you're
trying to get rid of that the basis
where where the internal can be
discerned. So if you don't give in blindly, but you
So if you don't give in blindly, but you
don't try to get rid of what has arisen,
but instead recognize it as the
wholeness of your situation because that
is a fact like oh there's a desire
towards this. I said no because I
learned I heard that I need to restrain
myself first.
Now what? Like do I now believe that
just through saying no no no no mind
will magically tame itself and free
itself from sensuality? No. So what do I
do? Well, I recognize
the experience as a whole of me being
pressured by desire towards this or
that, saying no to it, feeling
uncomfortable on account of it, and now
resisting that discomfort with aversion.
Because that's what you would see if you
don't blindly give in and don't try to
get rid of it. You will recognize, okay,
whether I like it or not, I am in the
situation of such and such kind, which
is the situation I just described. I'm
I'm trying to overcome this discomfort.
I used to try and overcome it by giving
into sense desires. Then I was told
that's bad. Then I was trying to
overcome it by doing this sua, by doing
this, by doing that. Either way, I'm
averse to it.
Why am I averse to it?
I'm not doing it. The mind is gripped.
But why do I take for granted the
aversion that it provides for me?
So that's how you actually overcome
hindrances internally and externally.
But if you're just seeing them or
assuming them to be on the level of
external sense objects,
you're not overcoming anything. Those
are not even hindrances correctly.
So through practice of self-awareness,
whether you're trying to go with your
desire or say no or try to get rid of it
because it's unpleasant. First and
foremost, you need to be self-aware of
whatever the experience is.
and then factually recognize okay yeah
mind cha is still liable towards these
pressures towards these pulls but I
can't just force it to drop it for force
the mind to just give it up but what I
can do is never lose perspective in
regard to that whole thing so again
Satipatana says he knows the mind of
lust as the mind of lust does not say
when mind of lust he does this and he
makes it into a mind of non-lust no you
will make it into a mind of non-lust by
knowing it as a lustful mind. That's how
you will subdue it and calm it down.
Because if you try to act out of the
mind of lust, any act you do will be
infected with lust. If you try to act
out of mind of ill will, anything you
do, even practice of meta will be driven
by that ill will. So he knows the mind
of lust as mind of lust. self-aware to
the extent of recognizing the chitta for
what it is and then not losing the sight
of that until it calms down. So that's
where the patient and patient endurance
ki comes in
otherwise you'll be just doing it on
your terms in other words otherwise
you'll be just doing it out of your own
desire and the same applies to the hindrance of
and the same applies to the hindrance of
doubt. Oh yeah, I think doubt is
probably going to be the first one
that's kind of the most obvious if you
can um
abandon like well if you can practice
correctly um
um
towards the hindrance of doubt
internally and externally
you will overcome the view
the fatter of doubt. So you still might
have doubt manifest internally or
externally but you would not be uh
established of view that the doubt comes
from the external counterparts
and a person might say well I don't
think that but the fact is just ask
yourself when there is a doubtful mind
do you immediately go and start
revolving around fixing it resolving the
doubt finding the answers that means you
still carry the view that the answers
come from the outside.
That's why it's like people can't even
follow their own reasoning,
their own intellect even when it's
accurate because it doesn't carry as
much weight for them that knowledge as
opposed to knowledge of some authority
externally saying what's right, what's
wrong. Or sometimes people can't even like
Or sometimes people can't even like
people note what they should do
internally like through their own
intellect and reasoning and
understanding but they can't do it until
somebody externally says even if it's
the same thing the somebody externally
tells them that's the way where they can
do it because the view has placed the
emphasis that the resolution of this
doubt of this pressure discomfort
dissonance that doesn't feel right comes
through finding the external clarity
and external means of affirmation of
what I need to do what I need to
practice and so on. Initially everybody
will start like that but the point will
come where you will know that I know
enough in a sense of information and
learning but what I'm doing now is like
whenever the mind pressures me with
doubt I take it for granted that I must
get rid of this I must resolve this so I
go back and I reread the text and I ask
more questions and I do the this or I or
I change up and I find something else
something to just appease this mind
externally which is no different than
finding sense objects pursuing sense
objects to appease ease the mental
craving the chitta's craving towards
sense desire true sense desire
so that's why like if you actually don't
give into the pressure of doubt and stay
with it and instead of but I must
resolve this because I'm not sure about
it instead of no I will resolve it when
there is no more pressure to resolve it
then I might choose to resolve it if
there is a genuine lack of information
I'm not sure about but for as long as
there is this compulsion to resolve it
that it's unpleasant
I will be fueling the hindrance of doubt
which means I will be maintaining the
fetter of the doubt that I that that I'm
fettered by. In other words, placing the
emphasis that doubt comes from the lack
of clarity from external things.
So if you don't act out of doubt long
enough, endure the mental pressure and be
endure the mental pressure and be
self-aware of it instead of trying to
resolve it, the emphasis will lessen and
eventually it would shift and you will
realize that the doubt comes from
doubtful chitta that has encountered
things suitable for doubt as the sutas
would say but the doubt never came from
the actual objects that you've been
perceiving or thinking about. Same with
sensuality. In so many sutas they would
have said no beautiful things remain in
the world. They're not sensuality. It
was the man's internal desire and lust.
Basically his thoughts affected with
that wrong emphasis. That's what his
sensuality is. The wise one who removes
that desire and lust. Beautiful things
remain standing unchanged. They never
were the origin of the problem. He was
the untrained chitta.
And that is why the sautapana is
described as both being confident and at
the same time independent of others.
>> Yes. Exactly. Yeah. He he he has seen
chitta sufficiently enough on that
internal basis that he cannot um fall
back into that wrong emphasis that the
clarity comes from the clarity of the
form or duty or virtue or performing the
precept or external authority. Just that
that's just cut off. That whole belief
is just cut off. gone cannot come back
because the sole reason for the
existence of that entire sphere of those
first three fetas was not seeing the
chitta as the sole reason for all these
problems for the craving for the duka
and so on.
Now once he sees it he won't be
mistaking it elsewhere but okay now he
needs to train that and that's the whole
uh training described in the sutras
that's why almost always when the Buddha
outlined practice of not almost every
single time when the Buddha outlined the
practice of assuba or meta um different
perceptions even that one kind of
contemplating thea or janna it was
always in reference to a noble disciple
that's already knows what the path is
already been doing it cuz now when he
does the asuba when he does the meta
he's doing it aiming at the chitta he's
doing it rightly he's not doing it just
as a reaction to what's being what he
feels oppresses him on account of saying
no to blindly following the desire and
and and and acting out
and that's the middle way and that's why
the middle way sounds simple yet it's
the hardest thing to see
like if if the Buddha if the Buddha's
teaching was would have been the way the
modern teravad is present ing it just
counter the perceptions anybody can do
it doesn't matter whether you're keeping
the precepts or not when this just think
that when that just think this it's like
well the Buddha would have said so he
would not have been talking about the
chitta and the training and the signs of
the mind and the necessary factors of
development and and the virtue and
restraint seclusion withdrawal for these
things to even become possible to be
seen he would just said no marks when
it's this just look at that
when it's that just look at this when
this bothers you, recite this mantra.
When that bothers you, recite that
mantra, no, that's just perversion and and
no, that's just perversion and and
bastardization pretty much by people
that hasn't haven't seen that middle
ground and all they see is just what's
written there and it's kind of flattened
and it just sounds like, okay, so when
it's A, I do the B. When it's B, if B
bothers me, I go back to A and I just do
that long enough until poof.
The mind just enlightens itself.
But like how can you do Janna if you're
not fully withdrawn from sensuality?
Because every single description in the
suta starts by being fully withdrawn
from sensuality as a prerequisite for
Janna. The pleasure of Janna comes from
not because of a mystical experience of
meditation but comes from being safe
from the dangerous domain of sensuality
and recognizing that
how can you do meta if you don't see
your own cheetah being sufficiently
enough seeing it not just like oh yeah
my cheetah is now this are you seeing it
as a independent entity inseparable from
you are you seeing mind affected with ill
are you seeing mind affected with ill
will as mind affected with ill will and
are you Are you okay with that? In other
words, are you able to contain that mind
affected with ill will? Or are you okay,
but now let me do meta? Why?
Because you're averse to the mind
affected wheel because it feels
uncomfortable, feels threatening, feels
unpleasant. Same with sensuality. That's
what I was saying people like you need
to start restraining because basically
for as long as you don't cultivate that
restraint sufficiently enough whether
you want it or not whether you think
about it or not you will believe you
will genuinely exist in the form of
belief that sensuality and desire comes
from sense objects
and then when you say no to that the
pain that comes as a result of it you
think it came because I said no
but if If you actually stop giving into
sensuality, regardless of what you
believe, stop fueling it. The time will
come when you recognize. In other words,
if you practice renunciation long
enough, you'll see that not just that
the renunciation doesn't cause the pain
of
that you experience when you say no to
something, it reveals it as something
that was already there.
So the pain that you experience when you
say no to your desires came from the
desires. Saying no just highlighted it.
But for somebody with a completely
skewed view of where the emphasis is,
sense objects, good bad just just linear
plus minus do not allow self-awareness
in regard to either means you're not
allowing the mind to be seen and
discerned which is a prerequisite for
sapati which means everything else that
the Buddha taught simply does not apply
to you.
And so you mentioned the free fatters in
relation to now discerning the chitta
rightly but how does personality view
fit into that? It's him the extent of
the emphasis on the external.
That's exactly what is.
It's the view that your kind of
say the center of your being, the center
of who you are, the center of I am, the
center of my point of view. It's
external to this experience as a whole.
In the same sense, the sensuality
is external to these desires to these
cravings to these actions.
That's why by addressing the wrong
emphasis that has proliferated into the
assumption of it comes from over there
all these things will disappear these
first three factors because that was the
common that was the basis for all three
of them.